An epic drama of adventure and exploration.
2001: A Space Odyssey is a science fiction, mystery,
adventure film directed by Stanley Kubrick.
Humanity finds a mysterious object buried beneath the lunar surface and sets off to find its
origins with the help of HAL 9000, the world's most advanced super computer.
Dr. David Bowman, played by Keir Dullea.
Dr. Frank Poole, played by Gary Lockwood.
Dr. Heywood Floyd, played by William Sylvester.
HAL 9000 (voice), played by Douglas Rain.
Moonwatcher, played by Daniel Richter.
Dr. Andrei Smyslov, played by Leonard Rossiter.
2001: A Space Odyssey is a 1968 epic science fiction film produced and directed
by Stanley Kubrick, who co-wrote the screenplay with Arthur C.
Its plot was inspired by several short stories optioned from Clarke,
primarily "The Sentinel" (1951) and "Encounter in the Dawn" (1953).
The film stars Keir Dullea, Gary Lockwood, William Sylvester, and Douglas Rain, and follows a voyage by astronauts,
scientists, and the sentient supercomputer HAL 9000 to Jupiter to investigate an alien monolith.
The film is noted for its scientifically accurate depiction of
spaceflight, pioneering special effects, and ambiguous themes.
Kubrick avoided conventional cinematic and narrative techniques; dialogue is
used sparingly, and long sequences are accompanied only by music.
Shunning the convention that major film productions should feature original music, 2001: A Space Odyssey takes for its soundtrack numerous
works of classical music, including pieces by Richard Strauss, Johann Strauss II, Aram Khachaturian, and György Ligeti.
Polarising critics after its release, 2001: A Space Odyssey has since been subject to a variety of
interpretations, ranging from the darkly apocalyptic to an optimistic reappraisal of the hopes of humanity.
Critics noted its exploration of themes such as human evolution, technology,
artificial intelligence, and the possibility of extraterrestrial life.
It was nominated for four Academy Awards, winning Kubrick the award for his direction of
the visual effects, the only Academy Award the director would receive.
The film is widely regarded as one of the greatest
and most influential films ever made.
In 1991, it was selected by the United States Library of Congress
for preservation in the National Film Registry.
In 2022, 2001: A Space Odyssey placed in the top ten of Sight & Sound's
decennial critics' poll, and topped their directors' poll.
A sequel, 2010: The Year We Make Contact, was released in 1984; it was based on
Clarke's novel 2010: Odyssey Two and made without Kubrick's involvement.
Clarke published a novelisation of 2001 (in part written concurrently with the screenplay) soon
after the film's 1968 release, for which Kubrick received co-writing credit.
The film explores themes of man vs machine, moon, jupiter,
artificial intelligence (a.i.), based on novel or book.
The tone is thought_provoking and mind_bending.